Poul Anderson

Gypsy

Gypsy

From afar, I caught a glimpse of the Traveler as my boat swung toward the planet. The great spaceship looked like a toy at that distance, a frail bubble of metal and air and energy against the enormous background of space. I thought of the machines within her, humming and whirring and clicking very faintly as they pursued their unending round of services, making that long hull into a living world—the hull that was now empty of life—and I had a sudden odd feeling of sympathy. As if she were alive, I felt that the Traveler was lonely.

The planet swelled before me, a shining blue shield blazoned with clouds and continents, rolling against a limitless dark and the bitterly burning stars. Harbor, we had named that world, the harbor at the end of our long journey, and there were few lovelier names. Harbor, haven, rest and peace and a sky overhead as roof against the naked blaze of space. It was good to get home.

I searched the heavens for another glimpse of the Traveler, but I couldn’t find her tiny form in that thronging wilderness of stars. No matter, she was still on her orbit about Harbor, moored to the planet, perhaps forever. I concentrated on bringing the spaceboat down.

Atmosphere whistled about the hull. After a month in the gloom and poisonous cold of the fifth planet, alone among utterly unhuman natives, I was usually on fire to get home and brought my craft down with a recklessness that overloaded the gravity beams. But this time I went a little more carefully, telling myself that I’d rather be late for supper than not arrive at all. Or perhaps it was that brief chance vision of the Traveler which made me suddenly thoughtful. After all, we had had some good times aboard her.

I sent the boat slanting toward the peninsula in the north temperate zone on which most of us were settled. The outraged air screamed behind me as I slammed down on the hard-packed earth that served us for a landing field. There were a few warehouses and service shops around it, long low buildings of the heavy timbers used by most of the colonists, and a couple of private homes a kilometer or so away. But otherwise only long grass rustled in the wind, gardens and wild groves, sunlight streaming out of a high blue sky. When I stepped from the boat, the fresh vivid scent of the land fairly leaped to meet me. I could hear the sea growling beyond the horizon.

Tokogama was on duty at the field. He was sitting on the porch of the office, smoking his pipe and watching the clouds sail by overhead, but he greeted me with the undemonstrative cordiality of old friends who know each other too well to need many words.

“So that’s the portmaster,” I said. “Soft touch. All you have to do is puff that vile-smelling thing and say hello to me.”

“That’s all,” he admitted cheerfully. “I am retained only for my uncommonly high ornamental value.”

It was, approximately, true. Our aircraft used the field with no formality, and we only kept this one space vessel in operation. The portmaster was on hand simply to oversee servicing and in the unlikely case of some emergency or dispute. But none of the colony’s few public posts—captain, communications officer, and the rest—required much effort in as simple a society as ours, and they were filled as spare-time occupations by anyone who wanted them. There was no compensation except getting first turn at using the machinery for farming or heavy construction which we owned in common.

“How was the trip?” asked Tokogama.

“Pretty good,” I said. “I gave them our machines and they filled my holds with their ores and alloys. And I managed to take a few more notes on their habits, and establish a few more code symbols for communication.”

“Which is a very notable brick added to the walls of science, but in view of the fact that you’re the only one who ever goes there it really makes no odds.” Tokogama’s dark eyes regarded me curiously. “Why do you keep on making those trips out there, Erling? Quite a few of the other boys wouldn’t mind visiting Five once in a while. Will and Ivan both mentioned it to me last week.”

“I’m no hog,” I said. “If either of them, or anyone else, wants a turn at the trading job, let ’em learn space piloting and they can go. But meanwhile—I like the work. You know that I was one of those who voted to continue the search for Earth.”

Tokogama nodded. “So you were. But that was three years ago. Even you must have grown some roots here.”

“Oh, I have,” I laughed. “Which reminds me I’m hungry, and judging by the sun it’s the local dinner time. So I’ll get on home, if Alanna knows I’m back.”

“She can’t help it,” he smiled. “The whole continent knows when you’re back, the way you rip the atmosphere coming in. That home cooking must have a powerful magnetic attraction.”

“A steak aroma of about fifty thousand gauss—” I turned to go, calling over my shoulder: “Why don’t you come to dinner tomorrow evening? I’ll invite the other boys and we’ll have an old-fashioned hot air session.”

“I was sort of hinting in that direction,” said Tokogama.

I got my carplane out of the hangar and took off with a whisper of air and a hum of grav-beam generators. But I flew low over the woods and meadows, dawdling along at fifty kilometers an hour and looking across the landscape. It lay quietly in the evening, almost empty of man, a green fair breadth of land veined with bright rivers. The westering sun touched each leaf and grass blade with molten gold, an aureate glow which seemed to fill the cool air like a tangible presence, and I could hear the chirp and chatter of the great bird flocks as they settled down in the trees. Yes—it was good to get home.

My own house stood at the very edge of the sea, on a sandy bluff sloping down to the water. The windy trees which grew about it almost hid the little stone and timber structure, but its lawns and gardens reached far, and beyond them were the fields from which we got our food. Down by the beach stood the boathouse and the little dock I had made, and I knew our sailboat lay waiting there for me to take her out. I felt an almost physical hunger for the sea again, the mighty surge of waves out to the wild horizon, the keen salt wind and the crying white birds. After a month in the sterile tanked air of the spaceboat, it was like being born again.

I set the plane down before the house and got out. Two small bodies fairly exploded against me—Einar and Mike. I walked into the house with my sons riding my shoulders.

Alanna stood in the doorway waiting for me. She was tall, almost as tall as I, and slim and red-haired and the most beautiful woman in the universe. We didn’t say much—it was unnecessary, and we were otherwise occupied for the next few minutes.

And afterward I sat before a leaping fire where the little flames danced and chuckled and cast a wavering ruddy glow over the room, and the wind whistled outside and rattled the door, and the sea roared on the nighted beach, and I told them of my fabulous space voyage, which had been hard and monotonous and lonely but was a glamorous adventure at home. The boys’ eyes never stirred from my face as I talked, I could feel the eagerness that blazed from them. The gaunt sun-seared crags of One, the misty jungles of Two, the mountains and deserts of Four, the great civilization of Five, the bitter desolation of the outer worlds—and beyond those the stars. But we were home now, we sat in a warm dry house and heard the wind singing outside.

I was happy, in a quiet way that had somehow lost the exuberance of my earlier returns. Content, maybe.

Oh, well, I thought. These trips to the fifth world were becoming routine, just as life on Harbor, now that our colony was established and our automatic and semiautomatic machines running smoothly, had quieted down from the first great riot of work and danger and work again. That was progress, that was what we had striven for, to remove want and woe and the knife-edged uncertainty which had haunted our days. We had arrived, we had graduated into a solid assurance and a comfort which still held enough unsureness and challenge to keep us from getting sluggish. Grown men don’t risk their necks climbing the uppermost branches of trees, the way children do; they walk on the ground, and when they have to rise they do so safely and comfortably, in a carplane.

“What’s the matter, Erling?” asked Alanna.

“Why—nothing.” I started out of my reverie, suddenly aware that the children were in bed and the night near its middle. “Nothing at all. I was just sitting thinking. A little tired, I guess. Let’s turn in.”

“You’re a poor liar, Erling,” she said softly. “What were you really thinking about?”

“Nothing,” I insisted. “That is, well, I saw the old Traveler as I was coming down today. It just put me in mind of old times.”

“It would,” she said. And suddenly she sighed. I looked at her in some alarm, but she was smiling again. “You’re right, it is late, and we’d better go to bed.”

I took the boys out in the sailboat the next day. Alanna stayed home on the excuse that she had to prepare dinner, though I knew of her theory that the proper psychodevelopment of children required a balance of paternal and maternal influence. Since I was away so much of the time, out in space or with one of the exploring parties which were slowly mapping our planet, she made me occupy the center of the screen whenever I was home.

Einar, who was nine years old and getting interested in the microbooks we had from the Traveler—and so, ultimately, from Earth—looked at her and said: “Back at Sol you wouldn’t have to make food, Mother. You’d just set the au…autochef, and come out with us.”

“I like to cook,” she smiled. “I suppose we could make autochefs, now that the more important semirobot machinery has been produced, but it’d take a lot of fun out of life for me.”

Her eyes went past the house, down to the beach and out over the restless sun-sparked water. The sea breeze ruffled her red hair, it was like a flame in the cool shade of the trees. “I think they must miss a lot in the Solar System,” she said. “They have so much there that, somehow, they can’t have what we’ve got—room to move about, lands that never saw a man before, the fun of making something ourselves.”

“You might like it if you went there,” I said. “After all, sweetheart, however wisely we may talk about Sol we know it only by hearsay.”

“I know I like what we have here,” she answered. I thought there was a faint note of defiance in her voice. “If Sol is just a legend, I can’t be sure I’d like the reality. Certainly it could be no better than Harbor.”

“All redheads are chauvinists,” I laughed, turning down toward the beach.

“All Swedes make unfounded generalizations,” she replied cheerfully. “I should’a known better than to marry a Thorkild.”

“Fortunately, Mrs. Thorkild, you didn’t.” I bowed.

The boys and I got out the sailboat. There was a spanking breeze, and in minutes we were scudding northward, along the woods and fields and tumbling surf of the coast.

“We should put a motor on the Naughty Nancy, Dad,” said Einar. “Suppose this wind don’t hold.”

“I like to sail,” I said. “The chance of having to man the sweeps is part of the fun.”

“Me too,” said Mike, a little ambiguously.

“Do they have sailboats on Earth?” asked Einar.

“They must,” I said, “since I designed the Nancy after a book about them. But I don’t think it’d ever be quite the same, Einar. The sea must always be full of boats, most of them powered, and there’d be aircraft overhead and some sort of building wherever you made landfall. You wouldn’t have the sea to yourself.”

“Then why’d you want to keep looking for Earth when ever’body else wanted to stay here?” he challenged.

A nine-year-old can ask some remarkably disconcerting questions. I said slowly: “I wasn’t the only one who voted to keep on searching. And—well, I admitted it at the time, it wasn’t Earth but the search itself that I wanted. I liked to find new planets. But we’ve got a good home now, Einar, here on Harbor.”

“I still don’t understand how they ever lost Earth,” he said.

“Nobody does,” I said. “The Traveler was carrying a load of colonists to Alpha Centauri—that was a star close to Sol—and men had found the hyperdrive only a few years before and reached the nearer stars. Anyway,something happened. There was a great explosion in the engines, and we found ourselves somewhere else in the galaxy, thousands of light-years from home. We don’t know how far from home, since we’ve never been able to find Sol again. But after repairing the ship, we spent more than twenty years looking. We never found home.” I added quickly, “Until we decided to settle on Harbor. That was our home.”

“I mean, how’d the ship get thrown so far off?”

I shrugged. The principles of the hyperdrive are difficult enough, involving as they do the concept of multiple dimensions and of discontinuous psi functions. No one on the ship—and everyone with a knowledge of physics had twisted his brains over the problem—had been able to figure out what catastrophe it was that had annihilated space-time for her. Speculation had involved space warps—whatever that term means, points of infinite discontinuity, un-dimensional fields, and Cosmos knows what else. Could we find what had happened, and purposefully control the phenomenon which had seized us by some blind accident, the galaxy would be ours. Meanwhile, we were limited to pseudovelocities of a couple of hundred lights, and interstellar space mocked us with vastness.

But how explain that to a nine-year-old? I said only: “If I knew that, I’d be wiser than anyone else, Einar. Which I’m not.”

***

“I wanna go swimming,” said Mike.

“Sure,” I said. “That was our idea, wasn’t it? We’ll drop anchor in the next bay—”

“I wanna go swimming in Spacecamp Cove.”

I tried to hedge, but Einar was all over me, too. It was only a few kilometers farther up the coast, and its broad sheltered expanse, its wide sandy beach, and the forest immediately behind, made it ideal for such an expedition. And after all, I had nothing against it.

Nothing—except the lure of the place.

I sighed and surrendered. Spacecamp Cove it was.

We had a good time there, swimming and picnicking, playing ball and loafing in the sand and swimming some more. It was good to lie in the sun again, with a cool wet wind blowing in from the sea and talking in the trees. And to the boys, the glamour of it was a sort of crown on the day.

But I had to fight the romance. I wasn’t a child any more, playing at spacemen and aliens, I was the grown man with some responsibilities. The community of the Traveler had voted by an overwhelming majority to settle on Harbor, and that was that.

And here, half hidden by long grass, half buried in the blowing sand, were the unmistakable signs of what we had left.

There wasn’t much. A few plasticontainers for food, a couple of broken tools of curious shape, some scattered engine parts. Just enough to indicate that a while ago—ten years ago, perhaps—a party of spacemen had landed here, camped for a while, made some repairs, and resumed their journey.

They weren’t from the fifth planet. Those natives had never left their world, and even with the technological impetus we were giving them in exchange for their metals they weren’t ever likely to, the pressures they needed to live were too great. They weren’t from Sol, or even some colony world—not only were the remains totally unlike our equipment, but the news of a planet like Harbor, almost a duplicate of Earth but without a native intelligent race, would have brought settlers here in swarms. So—somewhere in the galaxy, someone else had mastered the hyperdrive and was exploring space.

As we had been doing—

I did my best to be cheerful all the way home, and think I succeeded on the surface. And that in spite of Einar’s wildly romantic gabble about the unknown campers. But I couldn’t help remembering—

In twenty years of spacing, you can see a lot of worlds, and you can have a lot of experience. We had been gods of a sort, flitting from star to star, exploring, trading, learning, now and again mixing into the destinies of the natives. We had fought and striven, suffered and laughed and stood silent in wonder. For most of us, the dreadful hunger for home, the weariness of the hopeless quest, had shadowed that panorama of worlds which reeled through my mind. But—before Cosmos, I had loved every minute of it!

I fell into unrelieved moodiness as soon as we had stowed the Naughty Nancy in our boathouse. The boys ran ahead of me toward the house, but I followed slowly. Alanna met me at the door.

“Better wash up right away,” she said. “The company will be here any minute.”

“Uh-huh.”

She looked at me, for a very long moment, and laid her hand on my arm. In the long dazzling rays of the westering sun, her eyes were brighter than I had seen them before. I wondered if tears were not wavering just behind them.

“You were at Spacecamp Cove,” she said quietly.

“The boys wanted to go there,” I answered. “It’s a good place.”

“Erling—” She paused. I stood looking at her, thinking how beautiful she was. I remembered the way she had looked on Hralfar, the first time I kissed her. We had wandered a ways from the camp of the detail exploring that frosty little world and negotiating with its natives for supplies. The sky had been dark overhead, with a shrunken sun casting its thin pale light on the blue-shadowed snow. It was quiet, breathlessly quiet, the air was like sharp fire in our nostrils and her hair, the only color in that white horizon, seemed to crackle with frost. That was quite a long time ago, but nothing had changed between us since.

“Yes?” I prompted her. “Yes, what is it?”

Her voice came quickly, very low so the boys wouldn’t hear: “Erling, are you really happy here?”

“Why”—I felt an almost physical shock of surprise—“of course I am, dear. That’s a silly question.”

“Or a silly answer?” She smiled, with closed lips. “We did have some good times on the Traveler . Even those who grumbled loudest at the time admit that, now when they’ve got a little perspective on the voyage and have forgotten something of the overcrowding and danger and weariness. But you—I sometimes think the Traveler was your life, Erling.”

“I liked the ship, of course.” I had a somewhat desperate sense of defending myself. “After all, I was born and raised on her. I never really knew anything else. Our planetary visits were so short, and most of the worlds so unterrestrial. You liked it too.”

“Oh, sure, it was fun to go batting around the galaxy, never knowing what might wait at the next sun. But a woman wants a home. And—Erling, plenty of others your age, who also had never known anything else, hated it.”

“I was lucky. As an officer, I had better quarters, more privacy. And, well, that ‘something hid behind the ranges’ maybe meant more to me than to most others. But—good Cosmos, Alanna! you don’t think that now—”

“I don’t think anything, Erling. But on the ship you weren’t so absentminded, so apt to fall into daydreams. You didn’t sit around the place all day, you were always working on something….” She bit her lip. “Don’t misunderstand, Erling. I have no doubt you keep telling yourself how happy you are. You could go to your cremation, here on Harbor, thinking you’d had a rather good life. But—I sometimes wonder!”

“Now look—” I began.

“No, no, nothing more out of you. Get inside and wash up, the company’ll be coming in half a minute.”

I went, with my head in a whirl. Mechanically, I scrubbed myself and changed into evening blouse and slacks. When I came out of the bedroom, the first of the guests were already waiting.

MacTeague Angus was there, the old first mate of the Traveler and captain in the short time between Kane’s death and our settling on Harbor. So was my brother Thorkild Gustav, with whom I had little in common except a mutual liking. Tokogama Hideyoshi, Petroff Ivan, Ortega Manuel, and a couple of others showed up a few minutes later. Alanna took charge of their wives and children, and I mixed drinks all around.

For a while the talk was of local matters. We were scattered over quite a wide area, and had as yet not produced enough telescreens for every house, so that communication was limited to direct personal travel by plane. A hailstorm on Gustav’s farm, a minor breakdown in the vehicle factory superintended by Ortega, Petroff’s project of a fleet of semirobot fishing boats—small gossip. Presently dinner was served.

Gustav was rapturous over the steak. “What is it?” he asked.

“Some local animal I shot the other day,” I said. “Ungulate, reddish-brown, broad flat horns.”

“Oh, yes. Hm-m-m—I’ll have to try domesticating some. I’ve had pretty good luck with those glug-gugs.”

“Huh?” Petroff stared at him.

“Another local species,” laughed Gustav. “I had to call them something, and they make that kind of noise.”

“The Traveler was never like this,” said Ortega, helping himself to another piece of meat.

“I never thought the food was bad,” I said.

“No, we had the hydroponic vegetables and fruits, and the synthetic meats, as well as what we picked up on different planets,” admitted Ortega. But it wasn’t this good, ever. Hydroponics somehow don’t have the flavor of Earth-grown stuff.”

“That’s your imagination,” said Petroff. “I can prove—”

“I don’t care what you can prove, the facts remain.” Ortega glanced at me. “But there were compensations.”

“Not enough,” muttered Gustav. “I’ve got room to move, here on Harbor.”

“You’re being unjust to the Traveler, ” I said. “She was only meant to carry about fifty people for a short voyage at that. When she lost her way for twenty years, and a whole new generation got jammed in with their parents, it’s no wonder she grew crowded. Actually, her minimum crew is ten or so. Thirty people—fifteen couples, say, plus their kids—could travel in her in ease and comfort, with private apartments for all.”

“And still…still, for over twenty years, we fought and suffered and stood the monotony and the hopelessness—to find Earth.” Tokogama’s voice was musing, a little awed. “When all the time, on any of a hundred uninhabited terrestroid planets, we could have had—this.”

“For at least half that time,” pointed out MacTeague, “we were simply looking for the right part of the galaxy. We knew Sol wasn’t anywhere near, so we had no hopes to be crushed, but we thought as soon as the constellations began to look fairly familiar we’d be quickly able to find home.” He shrugged. “But space is simply too big, and our astrogational tables have so little information. Star travel was still in its infancy when we left Sol.

“An error of, say, one percent could throw us light-years off in the course of several hundred parsecs. And the galaxy is lousy with GO-type suns, which are statistically almost certain to have neighbors sufficiently like Sol’s to fool an unsure observer. If our tables had given positions relative to, say, S Doradus, we could have found home easily enough. But they used Sirius for their bright-star point—and we couldn’t find Sirius in that swarm of stars! We just had to hop from star to star which might be Sol—and find it wasn’t, and go on, with the sickening fear that maybe we were getting farther away all the time, maybe Sol lay just off the bows, obscured by a dark nebula. In the end—we gave it up as a bad job.”

“There’s more to it than that,” said Tokogama. “We realized all that, you know. But there was Captain Kane and his tremendous personality, his driving will to success, and we’d all come to rely more or less blindly on him. As long as he lived, nobody quite believed in the possibility of failure. When he died, everything seemed to collapse at once.”

I nodded grimly, remembering those terrible days that followed—Seymour’s mutinous attempt to seize power, bringing home to us just how sick and weary we all were; the arrival at this star which might have solved it all, might have given us a happy ending, if it had been Sol; the rest on Harbor, a rest which became a permanent stay—

“Something else kept us going all those years, too,” said Ortega quietly. “There was an element among the younger generation which liked to wander. The vote to stay here wasn’t unanimous.”

“I know,” said MacTeague. His level gaze rested thoughtfully on me. “I often wonder, Erling, why some of you don’t borrow the ship and visit the nearer stars, just to see what’s there.”

“Wouldn’t do any good,” I said tonelessly. “It’d just make our feet itch worse than ever—and there’d always be stars beyond those.”

“But why—” Gustav fumbled for words. “Why would anyone want to go—stargazing that way? I…well, I’ve got my feet on ground now, my own ground, my own home…it’s growing, I’m building and planting and seeing it come to reality before my own eyes, and it’ll be there for my children and their children. There’s air and wind and rain, sunlight, the sea, the woods and mountains—Cosmos! Who wants more? Who wants to trade it for sitting in a sterile metal tank, riding from star to star, homeless, hopeless?”

“Nobody,” I said hastily. “I was just trying—”

“The most pointless existence—simply to be a…a spectator in the universe!”

“Not exactly,” said Tokogama. “There was plenty we did, if you insist that somebody must do something. We brought some benefits of human civilization to quite a number of places. We did some extensive star-mapping, if we ever see Earthmen again they’ll find our tables useful, and our observations within different systems. We…well, we were wanderers, but so what? Do you blame a bird for not having hoofs?”

“The birds have hoofs now,” I said. “They’re walking on the ground. And”—I flashed a glance at Alanna—“they like it.”

The conversation was getting a little too hot. I steered it into safer channels until we adjourned to the living room. Over coffee and tobacco it came back.

We began reminiscing about the old days, planets we had seen, deeds we had done. Worlds and suns and moons, whirling through a raw dark emptiness afire with stars, were in our talk—strange races, foreign cities, lonely magnificence of mountains and plains and seas, the giant universe opening before us. Oh, by all the gods, we had fared far!

We had seen the blue hell-flames leaping over the naked peaks of a planet whose great sun almost filled its sky. We had sailed with a gang of happy pirates over a sea red as new-spilled blood toward the grotesque towers of a fortress older than their history. We had seen the rich color and flashing metal of a tournament on Drangor and the steely immensity of the continental cities on Alkan. We had talked philosophy with a gross wallowing cephalopod on one world and been shot at by the inhumanly beautiful natives of another. We had come as gods to a planet to lift its barbaric natives from the grip of a plague that scythed them down and we had come as humble students to the ancient laboratories and libraries of the next. We had come near perishing in a methane storm on a planet far from its sun and felt then how dear life is. We had lain on the beaches of the paradise world Luanha and let the sea sing us to sleep. We had ridden centauroids who conversed with us as they went to the aerial city of their winged enemies—

More than the wildly romantic adventures—which, after all, had been pretty dirty and bloody affairs at the time—we loved to remember the worlds themselves: a fiery sunset on the snowfields of Hralfar; a great brown river flowing through the rain forest which covered Atlang; a painted desert on Thyvari; the mighty disk of New Jupiter swelling before our bows; the cold and vastness and cruelty and emptiness and awe and wonder of open space itself. And, in our small clique of frank tramps, there had been the comradeship of the road, the calm unspoken knowledge of having friends who would stand firm—a feeling of belonging, such as men like Gustav had achieved only since coming here, and which we seemed to have lost.

Lost—yes, why not admit it? We didn’t see each other very often any more, we were too scattered, too busy. And the talk of the others was just a little bit boring.

Well, it couldn’t be helped—

It was late that night when the party broke up. Alanna and I saw the guests out to their planes. When the last vehicle had whispered into the sky, we stood for a while looking around us. The night was very still and cool, with a high starry sky in which the moon of Harbor was rising. Its light glittered on the dew under our feet, danced restlessly on the sea, threw a dim silver veil on the dreaming land—our land.

I looked down at Alanna. She was staring over the darkened view, staring as if she had never seen it before—or never would again. The moonlight was tangled like frost in her hair. What if I never see open space again? What if I sit here till I die? This is worth it.

She spoke at last, very slowly, as if she had to shape each word separately: “I’m beginning to realize it. Yes, I’m quite sure.”

“Sure of what?” I asked.

“Don’t play dumb. You know what I mean. You and Manuel and Ivan and Hideyoshi and the others who were here—except Angus and Gus, of course. And quite a few more. You don’t belong here. None of you.”

“How—so?”

“Look, a man who had been born and raised in a city, and had a successful life in it, couldn’t be expected to take to the country all of a sudden. Maybe never. Put him among peasants, and he’d go around all the rest of his life wondering vaguely why he wasn’t honestly happy.”

“We—Now don’t start that again, sweetheart,” I begged.

“Why not? Somebody’s got to. After all, Erling, this is a peasantry we’ve got, growing up on Harbor. More or less mechanized, to be sure, but still rooted to the soil, close to it, with the peasant strength and solidity and the peasant’s provincial outlook. Why, if a ship from Earth landed tomorrow, I don’t think twenty people would leave with it.

“But you, Erling, you and your friends—you grew up in the ship, and you made a successful adaptation to it. You spent your formative years wandering. By now—you’re cosmopolites. For you, a mountain range will always be more than it really is, because of what’s behind it. One horizon isn’t enough, you’ve got to have many, as many as there are in the universe.

“Find Earth? Why, you yourself admitted you don’t care whether Earth is ever found. You only want the search.

“You’re a gypsy, Erling. And no gypsy could ever be tied to one place.”

I stood for a long while, alone with her in the cold calm moonlight, and said nothing. When I looked down at her, finally, she was trying not to cry, but her lip was trembling and the tears were bright in her eyes. Every word was wrenched out of me:

“You may be right, Alanna. I’m beginning to be horribly afraid you are. But what’s to be done about it?”

“Done?” She laughed, a strangely desolate laugh. “Why, it’s a very simple problem. The answer is circling right there up in the sky. Get a crew who feel the way you do, and take the Traveler . Go roaming—forever!”

“But…you? You, the kids, the place here…you—”

“Don’t you see?” Her laughter rang louder now, echoing faintly in the light night. “Don’t you see? I want to go, too!” She almost fell into my arms. “I want to go, too!”

There is no reason to record the long arguments, grudging acceptances, slow preparations. In the end we won. Sixteen men and their wives, with half a dozen children, were wild to leave.

That summer blazed up into fall, winter came, spring, and summer again, while we made ready. Our last year on Harbor. And I had never realized how much I loved the planet. Almost, I gave up.

But space, free space, the open universe and the ship come alive again—!

We left the colony a complete set of plans, in the unlikely event that they should ever want to build a starship of their own, and a couple of spaceboats and duplicates of all the important automatic machinery carried by the Traveler . We would make astrogating tables, as our official purpose, and theoretically we might some day come back.

But we knew we never would. We would go traveling, and our children would carry the journey on after us, and their children after them, a whole new civilization growing up between the stars, rootless but tremendously alive. Those who wearied of it could always colonize a planet; we would be spreading mankind over the galaxy. When our descendants were many, they would build other ships until there was a fleet, a mobile city hurtling from sun to sun. It would be a culture to itself, drawing on the best which all races had to offer and spreading it over the worlds. It would be the bloodstream of the interstellar civilization which was slowly gestating in the universe.

As the days and months went by, my boys grew even more impatient to be off. I smiled a little. Right now, they only thought of the adventure of it, romantic planets and great deeds to be done. Well, there were such, they would have eventful lives, but they would soon learn that patience and steadfastness were needed, that there was toil and suffering and danger—and life!

Alanna—I was a little puzzled. She was very gay when I was around, merrier than I had ever seen her before. But she often went out for long walks, alone on the beach or in the sun-dappled woods, and she started a garden which she would never harvest. Well—so it went, and I was too busy with preparations to think much about it.

The end came, and we embarked on the long voyage, the voyage which has not ceased yet and, I hope, will never end. The night before, we had Angus and Gustav in for a farewell party, and it was a strange feeling to be saying good-bye knowing that we would never see them again, or hear from them. It was like dying.

But we were alone in the morning. We went out to our carplane, to fly to the landing field where the gypsies would meet. From there, a boat would take us to the Traveler . I still could not fully realize that I was captain—I, captain of the great ship which had been my world, it didn’t seem real. I walked slowly, my head full of the sudden universe of responsibility.

Alanna touched my arm. “Look around, Erling,” she whispered. “Look around at our land. You’ll never see it again.”

I shook myself out of my reverie and let my eyes sweep the horizon. It was early, the grass was still wet, flashing in the new sun. The sea danced and glittered beyond the rustling trees, crying its old song to the fair green land, and the wind that blew from it was keen and cold and pungent with life. The fields were stirring in the wind, a long ripple of grass, and high overhead a bird was singing.

“It’s—very beautiful,” I said.

“Yes.” I could hardly hear her voice. “Yes, it is. Let’s go, Erling.”

We got into the carplane and slanted skyward. The boys crowded forward with me, staring ahead for the first glimpse of the landing field, not seeing the forests and meadows and shining rivers that slipped away beneath us.

Alanna sat behind me, looking down over the land. Her bright head was bent away so I couldn’t see her face. I wondered what she was thinking, but somehow I didn’t want to ask her.